<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<page dest="amenirdis_outer.html">
  <name>Outer Coffin of Amenirdis (PAHMA 5-1404 a,b)</name>
  <creator>Kea Johnston</creator>
  <model src="${assets}/amenirdis_outer/amenirdis_outer.gltf" dest="models/amenirdis_outer.gltf">
    <link name="hitbox_text_1" ref="text1"/>
  </model>
  <description>
    <contents>
      <p>
        This coffin is one of a pair which belonged to a woman named Amenirdis. This is her outer
        coffin, which takes the form of a four-posted shrine. This type of coffin is sometimes called a
        qrs.t coffin. Amenirdis' second coffin, an anthropoid coffin, nested inside this one can be seen
        here [link to other Amenirdis coffin]. William Randolph Hearst brought both of Amenirdis'
        coffins back from Egypt in February of 1903. Amenirdis' mummy is not in the museum's
        collection and her ultimate fate is a mystery. We suspect because of her name, titles, and the
        style of her coffins that Amenirdis lived in the area of Thebes during the 25th or 26th dynasty.
        Amenirdis' name is common for this time period, but we have not yet found another
        monument which may belong to this particular Amenirdis, who is the daughter of a lector priest
        named Iwefaaw. We are still researching Amenirdis' background and family, so check back for
        updates.
      </p>
    </contents>
  </description>
  <texts>
    <text id="text1">
      <desc>center column lid</desc>
      <himg src="${assets}/amenirdis_outer/amenirdis_outer_full.svg" dest="img/amenirdis_outer_full.svg"/>
      <al encoding="mdc">
        Htp di nsw.t n wsir-skr nb ST(y.t) di=f pr.t-xrw tA irp kA(.w) Apd(.w) snTr qbH mw irp x.t nb(.t) nfr(.t) N kA n Hsy(.t) Xnw n Imn imn-ir-di=s.t {t}&lt;sA&gt;.t Xry-Hb.t n s.t mAa.t iw=f-aA-w 
      </al>
      <tr xml:lang="en">
        Royal offerings of Osiris-Sokar, lord of the Shetit-shrine that he might give a voice offering of
        bread and wine, beef and poultry, incense and cool water, wine, and everything good for the Ka
        of the Singer of the Interior of Amun, Amunirdis, daughter of the ritualist priest in the Place of
        Truth, Iwefaaw.
      </tr>
    </text>
  </texts>
  <footnotes>
    <!--  to be linked in the content becaues only <p> can nest <fnref num="4"/>
    <fn num="1">Ranke, Hermann, Die Ägyptische Personennamen, 3 vols (Glückstadt: J. J. Augustin, 1935), I, p 14, n 3.</fn>
    <fn num="2">Christian Leitz, Lexikon der ägyptischen Götter und Götterbezeichnungen, Orientalia Lovaniensia Analecta (OLA),
    112 (Leuven: Peeters, 2002), III, p. 755.</fn>
    -->
  </footnotes>
</page>
