<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<page dest="irethoreru_famsf.html">
  <name>Irethoreru at FAMSF</name>
  <creator>Kea Johnston</creator>
  <model src="${assets}/irethoreru_famsf/irethoreru_famsf.gltf" dest="models/irethoreru_famsf.gltf">
    <link name="text_1_col_1" ref="text1col1"/>
    <link name="text_1_col_2" ref="text1col2"/>
    <link name="text_1_col_3" ref="text1col3"/>
    <link name="text_1_col_4" ref="text1col4"/>
    <link name="text_1_col_5" ref="text1col5"/>
    <link name="text_1_col_6" ref="text1col6"/>
    <link name="text_1_col_7" ref="text1col7"/>
    <link name="text_1_col_8" ref="text1col8"/>
    <link name="text_1_col_9" ref="text1col9"/>

  </model>
  <description>
    <contents xml:lang="en">
      <p><!--  where to put footnotes in this section-->
        The coffin of Irethoreru was donated to the (now) de Young Museum in San Francisco in 1917 by local businessman Jeremiah Lynch, who acquired it on a trip to Egypt in 1889. Five years prior to Lynch's visit, the cemeteries of the site of Akhmim (from which Irethoreru's coffin must have originated) were discovered by Egyptologist Gaston Maspero. The site's rich cemeteries were systematically plundered by official and unofficial excavations throughout the 1880s, and antiquities from the site flooded the art market to be subsequently snapped up by European and American tycoons like Lynch.

        Through most of the 20th century, the coffin and remains of Irethoreru were on long-term loan to the Haggin Museum in Stockton, CA. During this time, Dr. Patricia Podzorski undertook the first translation of the coffin.[1] The loan ended in 2009, and the Haggin Museum threw a good-bye party for Irethoreru, who had been a part of the community for a generation.[2] Studies of Irethoreru's remains and coffin undertaken by Dr Renée Dreyfus and Dr Jonathan Elias since his return to the Fine Arts Museum of San Francisco have revealed much more about who Irethoreru was in life.

        An examination of Irethoreru's skeleton shows that he was at least 25 years old, but probably closer to 45.[3]  In life, he was a stolist priest of Min at Akhmim. This was a common title given to priests who had the duty of clothing the statues of ithyphallic gods. Additionally, Irethoreru was a priest of Osiris Sokar and also held the title of "fkty" or "bald" priest in the "House of the Sister". The location of this institution is unknown, which is not particularly surprising given the paucity of remains which can be definitively associated with the Akhmim temples. Irethoreru's coffin can be stylistically dated between the Saite Period (Dynasty 26) and the early Ptolemaic period, giving us a timeframe for when he lived: ~600-300 BCE.[4] The layout of the decoration on the coffin is very rare, and the closest parallel stylistically is the coffin of Minirdis at the Field Museum in Chicago.[5]

        Irethoreru's father, a man named Ankhwenennefer, held the same titles as Irethoreru. Dr. Jonathan Elias proposes that Irethoreru was the son of the same Ankhwenennefer whose coffins and remains are now in the Washington State Historical Society in Tacoma and that his great uncle was the same Irethoreru whose coffin is now in the British Museum as (EA20745).[6] However, the owner of the coffins in Tacoma seems to have been much more highly ranked than Irethoreru's father. The relationship between Irethoreru's father Ankhwenennefer and the Ankhwenennefer in Tacoma remains unknown.

        Irethoreru's mother, Tadikhonsuiiti, has a long and interesting titulary which has proven enigmatic in all translations. One of her titles is "shemayt" (šmꜣy.t) priestess of Min. This title is mentioned in Theban temple reliefs depicting the festival of Min-Amun and dating to the 19th dynasty and the Ptolemaic period. In the later reliefs, the title is the name of a goddess. In the earlier reliefs, the role of the Shemayt priestess was performed by the queen, who used a combination of dance and chant in a ritual for the purpose of rejuvenating and re-empowering the king.[7] Irethoreru's mother was neither a queen nor a goddess, and the extent to which the Min-Festival rituals at Akhmim resembled those at Thebes is unknown, especially since it seems unlikely that the king would have appeared at the Akhmim temple to participate in them. Tadikhonsuiiti's other title, Pure Priestess of the Creator of the Ennead, is otherwise unknown. It is our hope that further study of religious life in the Egyptian provinces and further excavations at Akhmim will reveal more about the roles of Irethoreru and his parents in their community.
      </p>
    </contents>
  </description>
  <texts>
    <text id = "text1">
      <desc>
            Central columns on lid, reading retrograde and containing Book of the dead spell 51/52.
      </desc>
      <frag id="text1col1">
        <himg src="${assets}/irethoreru_famsf/texts/text1col1.svg" dest="img/irethoreru_famsf_text1col1.svg"/>
        <!-- Assume we are not doing hi element anymore -->
        <hi encoding="mdc-jsesh"></hi> 
        <al encoding="mdc">
        Dd mdw in wsir ir-Hr-irw sA n hr-ir-sn ms n nb(.t) pr t(A)-di-wsir mAa(.t) [xrw]  
        i.nD Hr=Tn nb.w tA Sw(i.w) &lt;i&gt;sf.t wnn.(y)w a[n]x r nHH Hn.ty D.t  
        wbA=Tn wi r tA &lt;t&gt;w=i Ax.k..
        </al>
        <tr xml:lang="en">
        Recitation by the Osiris Irethoriru, son of Herirsen, whom the lady of the house Tadiusir bore, justified. 
        Hail to you, lords of right who are free from chaos, who are continuously existing, alive, for cyclical time, lasting forever.  
        May you reveal me to the land, for I am an Akh…
        </tr>

      </frag>
      <frag id="text1col2">
        <himg src="${assets}/irethoreru_famsf/texts/text1col2.svg" dest="img/irethoreru_famsf_text1col2.svg"/>
        <al encoding="mdc">
        ...wy sxm.{nb}&lt;k&gt;wi m HkA=T(n) ip{t}.kw m [ip.t]=Tn  
        tnHm=Tn wi m Ad(w) im(y) iw n mAa.tyw di{t}=T{S}&lt;n&gt;n=i r=i {i}&lt;m&gt;t.t…
        </al>
        <tr xml:lang="en">
        …in your form! I am powerful with your magic, and I am counted among your number! 
        May you rescue me from the crocodile who is in the Island of the Righteous. May you give me my mouth that I may take speak…
        </tr>
      </frag>
      <frag id="text1col3">
        <himg src="${assets}/irethoreru_famsf/texts/text1col3.svg" dest="img/irethoreru_famsf_text1col3.svg"/>
        <al encoding="mdc">
        ...=i im=f im(i) di=tw n=i Aw.t-a n-m-bAH=Tn Hr-nt.t tw=i r{T}x.kwi {r}=Tn ir-&lt;r&gt;x.kwi  
        rn n nTr pf aA di=Tn DfA.w r fn.t=f n-k-A-w rn=f iw=f w…
        </al>
        <tr xml:lang="en">
        ...with it. Let offerings be given to me in your presence, because I know you, and I know  
        the name of that great god to whose nose you give provisions. Nekau is his name. He…
        </tr>
      </frag>
      <frag id="text1col4">
        <himg src="${assets}/irethoreru_famsf/texts/text1col4.svg" dest="img/irethoreru_famsf_text1col4.svg"/>
        <al encoding="mdc">
        ...&lt;bA&gt;{fw} Ax.t iAb.t n.t p.t iw=f {iw=f} wbA{=f} r Ax.t imn.t n.t p.t  
        rwi=i r rwi {iT}=f wDA.t=i wDA.t=f TAs pXr n dr=Tw wi Hr ms[q.t]  
        n sxm sbi.w im=i {iw=}...
        </al>
        <tr xml:lang="en">
        …opens up the eastern horizon of the sky, and he opens up the western horizon of the sky.  
        I expel as he expels. My flourishing is his flourishing (and vice-versa). I will not be subdued in the Msqt-Heavens!  
        Wrongdoers will have no power over me.
        </tr>
      </frag>
      <frag id="text1col5">
        <himg src="${assets}/irethoreru_famsf/texts/text1col5.svg" dest="img/irethoreru_famsf_text1col5.svg"/>
        <al encoding="mdc">
        ...{=i} n Sn=tn &lt;w&gt;i Hr sbA.w=Tn n xtm=[T]&lt;n&gt; aA.wy=&lt;t&gt;n Hr=i  
        t=i m p Hn&lt;q&gt;.t=i m dp i smA a.wy=&lt;i&gt; m Hw.t-nTr rti=f n=i itm zmnx n=f n=i pr im {rx.t}
        </al>
        <tr xml:lang="en">
        You will not hold me back from your gateways. You will not seal your doors to me.  
        My bread is in Pe and my beer is in Dep. O, join my arms in the temple! He has given Atum to me. He has established a house for me there.
        </tr>
      </frag>
      <frag id="text1col6">
        <himg src="${assets}/irethoreru_famsf/texts/text1col6.svg" dest="img/irethoreru_famsf_text1col6.svg"/>
        <al encoding="mdc">
        &lt;iti&gt; bty im=f n rx tnw nb.w ir n=i Hb(.w) im=f (i)n ip(w) sA=i n D(.t)=i  
        di=T n=i prt-xrw t {t} &lt;Hnq.t&gt; irp kA.w Apd.w xt nb nfr wab bnr anx nTr im wnn=i mn.{T}&lt;k&gt;wi
        </al>
        <tr xml:lang="en">
        Emmer and barley are in it of an unknowable amount. Festivals are done for me in it by this, my own son.  
        May you grant to me an invocation offering: bread, beer, wine meat, fowl, and every good and sweet thing on which a god lives. I exist established…
        </tr>
      </frag>
      <frag id="text1col7">
        <himg src="${assets}/irethoreru_famsf/texts/text1col7.svg" dest="img/irethoreru_famsf_text1col7.svg"/>
        <al encoding="mdc">
        n D.t m xpr.w nb.w mr=i xnti=i m sx.t (i)Arw xnti=i m sx.t Htp.w in&lt;k&gt; {i}p&lt;w&gt; rw.ty  
        imAx{t}(w) n wsir ir(.t)-{n}-Hr-{n}-i&lt;r&gt;w psS mw.t&lt;=k&gt; nw.t Hr=k m rn=s
        </al>
        <tr xml:lang="en">
        …forever in all the forms I wish. May I sail up to the Field of Reeds. May I sail up to the Field of Offerings. It is I, Ruty!  
        The venerated Osiris Irethoriru: (Your) mother Nut spreads over you in her name of…
        </tr>
      </frag>
      <frag id="text1col8">
        <himg src="${assets}/irethoreru_famsf/texts/text1col8.svg" dest="img/irethoreru_famsf_text1col8.svg"/>
        <al encoding="mdc">
        m Apr.t di=&lt;z&gt; wnn=k m nTr m xf.t r=f &lt;m r&gt;n=s m nTr tw wr m msw.(t)=s &lt;H&gt;tp gb  
        mr=s.t tw xw-n=f tw di DHwty tm (i)r(y.t)=f pr=k aq=k ra-nb nHH Htp Hr…
        </al>
        <tr xml:lang="en">
        …”Aperet-pet”. She causes that you become a god without an enemy against you in her name of “God(dess)" You are the eldest of her children. Geb is satisfied.  
        She loves you, and He protected you. Thoth causes what is against him to not exist. May you come out, and may you go in every day, for cyclical eternity, with..
        </tr>
      </frag>
      <frag id="text1col9">
        <himg src="${assets}/irethoreru_famsf/texts/text1col9.svg" dest="img/irethoreru_famsf_text1col9.svg"/>
        <al encoding="mdc">
        ...=k n SnA=kHr aA.wy n.w dwA.t &lt;aq&gt;=k m qar ra-nb imAx n wsir ir.t-Hr-i&lt;r&gt;w sA H&lt;r-ir&gt;=zn {f} ms &lt;n nb.t&gt; pr  
        &lt;tA&gt;-di-wsir mAa-xrw m nb mAa.t rx wsx.t n mAa.ty
        </al>
        <tr xml:lang="en">
        …your face content. You shall not be turned away from the doors of the Duat! May you (enter) the shrine every day.  Revered one of Osiris, Irethoriru, son of Herirsen, who the lady of the house  
        Tadiusir bore, justified, as a lord of truth who knows how to come out from the hall of two truths.
        </tr>
      </frag>
    </text>
  </texts>
  <footnotes>
    <!--  to be linked in the content becaues only <p> can nest <fnref num="4"/>
    <fn num="1">The scribe on this coffin does not differentiate between Gardiner A1 and Gardiner A2</fn>
    <fn num="2">CHere, the glyph Gardiner D5 should have perhaps been used be instead of Gardiner U1.</fn>
    <fn num="3">Htp-kA, Wb 3, 195.1</fn>
    <fn num="4">The phrase Iw=f-aA is here taken to be the name of the deceased, inserted into the middle of the spell.
      The spelling with the bookroll determinative is odd, but is paralleled by the spelling of the name of the
      name of the deceased in the offering formula on the sides of the proposed inner coffin of this individual,
      PAHMA 6-19928</fn>
    <fn num="5">The spell after the word nh.t is a bit garbled. The last two signs seem to be determinatives for bread, but
      they are partially worn away, and the most that can be said about them is that they are probably long, flat
      signs.</fn>
    -->
  </footnotes>
</page>
