<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<page dest="irethoreru_famsf.html">
  <name>Irethoreru at FAMSF</name>
  <creator>Kea Johnston</creator>
  <model src="${assets}/irethoreru_famsf/irethoreru_famsf.gltf" dest="models/irethoreru_famsf.gltf">
    <link name="text_1_col_1" ref="text1col1"/>
    <link name="text_1_col_2" ref="text1col2"/>
    <link name="text_1_col_3" ref="text1col3"/>
    <link name="text_1_col_4" ref="text1col4"/>
    <link name="text_1_col_5" ref="text1col5"/>
    <link name="text_1_col_6" ref="text1col6"/>
    <link name="text_1_col_7" ref="text1col7"/>
    <link name="text_1_col_8" ref="text1col8"/>
    <link name="text_1_col_9" ref="text1col9"/>
  </model>
  <description>
    <contents xml:lang="en">
       <p>
        This cedar-wood coffin belonging to a man named Irethoriru was once brilliantly painted, 
        but only traces of its color remain: some blue-green stripes can still be seen behind the right ear 
        and some white cement might have been used to set glass inlays into the central inscription. 
        The coffin is stylistically similar to those made in the 30th dynasty and the early Ptolemaic period, 
        so Irethoriru probably lived during this time. The coffin gives the names of his mother and father,
        but we know little else about him at this point, other than that he was wealthy enough to afford a coffin made
        from imported wood.
      </p>
      <p>
        The texts consist of a version of Book of the Dead Spell 72, 
        followed by a "Nut Spell" derived from Pyramid Text 368.
      </p>
      <p>
        The coffin of Irethoriru was gifted to the Fine Arts Museums of San Francisco by Diane B. Wilsley
        in honor of Alfred S. Wilsley.</p>     
    </contents>
  </description>
  <texts>
    <text id = "text1">
      <desc>9 Columns of text on the front of the coffin lid, stretching from the chest to the ankles.</desc>
      <frag id="text1col1">
        <himg src="${assets}/irethoreru_famsf/texts/text1col1.svg" dest="img/irethoreru_famsf_text1col1.svg"/>
        <!-- Assume we are not doing hi element anymore -->
        <hi encoding="mdc-jsesh"></hi> 
        <al encoding="mdc">
        Dd mdw in wsir ir-Hr-irw sA n hr-ir-sn <fnref num="1"/> ms n nb(.t) pr t(A)-di-wsir mAa(.t) [xrw]  
        i.nD Hr=Tn nb.w tA Sw(i.w) &lt;i&gt;sf.t wnn.(y)w a[n]x r nHH Hn.ty<fnref num="2"/> D.t  
        wbA=Tn wi r tA &lt;t&gt;w=i Ax.k..
        </al>
        <tr xml:lang="en">
        Recitation by the Osiris Irethoriru, son of Herirsen, whom the lady of the house Tadiusir bore, justified. 
        Hail to you, lords of right <fnref num="3"/> who are free from chaos, who are continuously existing, alive, for cyclical time, lasting forever.  
        May you reveal me to the land, for I am an Akh…
        </tr>

      </frag>
      <frag id="text1col2">
        <himg src="${assets}/irethoreru_famsf/texts/text1col2.svg" dest="img/irethoreru_famsf_text1col2.svg"/>
        <al encoding="mdc">
        ...wy sxm.{nb}&lt;k&gt;wi m HkA=T(n) ip{t}.kw m [ip.t]=Tn  
        tnHm=Tn wi m Ad(w) im(y) iw n mAa.tyw di{t}=T{S}<fnref num="4"/>&lt;n&gt;n=i r=i {i}&lt;m&gt;t.t…
        </al>
        <tr xml:lang="en">
        …in your form! I am powerful with your magic, and I am counted among your number! 
        May you rescue me from the crocodile who is in the Island of the Righteous. May you give me my mouth that I may take speak…
        </tr>
      </frag>
      <frag id="text1col3">
        <himg src="${assets}/irethoreru_famsf/texts/text1col3.svg" dest="img/irethoreru_famsf_text1col3.svg"/>
        <al encoding="mdc">
        ...=i im=f im(i) di=tw n=i Aw.t-a n-m-bAH=Tn Hr-nt.t tw=i r{T}x.kwi {r}=Tn ir-&lt;r&gt;x.kwi  
        rn n nTr pf aA di=Tn DfA.w r fn.t=f n-k-A-w <fnref num="5"/> rn=f iw=f w…
        </al>
        <tr xml:lang="en">
        ...with it. Let offerings be given to me in your presence, because I know you, and I know  
        the name of that great god to whose nose you give provisions. Nekau is his name. He…
        </tr>
      </frag>
      <frag id="text1col4">
        <himg src="${assets}/irethoreru_famsf/texts/text1col4.svg" dest="img/irethoreru_famsf_text1col4.svg"/>
        <al encoding="mdc">
        ...&lt;bA&gt;{fw} Ax.t iAb.t n.t p.t iw=f {iw=f} wbA{=f} r Ax.t imn.t n.t p.t  
        rwi=i r rwi {iT}=f wDA.t=i wDA.t=f TAs pXr n dr=Tw wi Hr ms[q.t]  
        n sxm sbi.w im=i {iw=}...
        </al>
        <tr xml:lang="en">
        …opens up the eastern horizon of the sky, and he opens up the western horizon of the sky.  
        I expel as he expels. My flourishing is his flourishing (and vice-versa). I will not be subdued in the Msqt-Heavens!  
        Wrongdoers will have no power over me.
        </tr>
      </frag>
      <frag id="text1col5">
        <himg src="${assets}/irethoreru_famsf/texts/text1col5.svg" dest="img/irethoreru_famsf_text1col5.svg"/>
        <al encoding="mdc">
        ...{=i} n Sn=tn &lt;w&gt;i Hr sbA.w=Tn n xtm=[Tn]<fnref num="6"/> aA.wy n Hr=i  
        t=i m p Hn&lt;q&gt;.t=i m dp i smA a.wy=&lt;i&gt; m Hw.t-nTr rti=f n=i itm zmnx n=f n=i pr im {rx.t}
        </al>
        <tr xml:lang="en">
        You will not hold me back from your gateways. You will not seal the doors to me.  
        My bread is in Pe and my beer is in Dep. O, join my arms in the temple! He has given Atum to me. He has established a house for me there.
        </tr>
      </frag>
      <frag id="text1col6">
        <himg src="${assets}/irethoreru_famsf/texts/text1col6.svg" dest="img/irethoreru_famsf_text1col6.svg"/>
        <al encoding="mdc">
        &lt;iti&gt; bty im=f n rx tnw nb.w ir n=i Hb(.w) im=f (i)n ip(w) sA=i n D(.t)=i  
        di=T n=i prt-xrw t {t} &lt;Hnq.t&gt; irp kA.w Apd.w xt nb nfr wab bnr anx nTr im wnn=i mn.{T}&lt;k&gt;wi
        </al>
        <tr xml:lang="en">
        Emmer and barley are in it of an unknowable amount. Festivals are done for me in it by this,<fnref num="7"/> my own son.  
        May you grant to me an invocation offering: bread, beer, wine meat, fowl, and every good and sweet thing on which a god lives. I exist established…
        </tr>
      </frag>
      <frag id="text1col7">
        <himg src="${assets}/irethoreru_famsf/texts/text1col7.svg" dest="img/irethoreru_famsf_text1col7.svg"/>
        <al encoding="mdc">
        n D.t m xpr.w nb.w mr=i xnti=i m sx.t (i)Arw xnti=i m sx.t Htp.w in&lt;k&gt; {i}p&lt;w&gt; rw.ty  
        imAx{t}(w) n wsir ir(.t)-{n}-Hr-{n}-i&lt;r&gt;w psS mw.t&lt;=k&gt; nw.t Hr=k m rn=s
        </al>
        <tr xml:lang="en">
        …forever in all the forms I wish. May I sail up to the Field of Reeds. May I sail up to the Field of Offerings. It is I, Ruty!  
        <fnref num="8"/>The venerated Osiris Irethoriru: (Your) mother Nut spreads over you in her name of…
        </tr>
      </frag>
      <frag id="text1col8">
        <himg src="${assets}/irethoreru_famsf/texts/text1col8.svg" dest="img/irethoreru_famsf_text1col8.svg"/>
        <al encoding="mdc">
        m Apr.t di=&lt;z&gt; wnn=k m nTr m xf.t r=f &lt;m r&gt;n=s m nTr tw wr m msw.(t)=s &lt;H&gt;tp gb  
        mr=s.t tw xw-n=f tw di DHwty tm (i)r(y.t)=f pr=k aq=k ra-nb nHH Htp Hr…
        </al>
        <tr xml:lang="en">
        …”Aperet-pet”. She causes that you become a god without an enemy against you in her name of “God(dess)" You are the eldest of her children. Geb is satisfied.  
        She loves you, and He protected you. Thoth causes what is against him to not exist. May you come out, and may you go in every day, for cyclical eternity, with..
        </tr>
      </frag>
      <frag id="text1col9">
        <himg src="${assets}/irethoreru_famsf/texts/text1col9.svg" dest="img/irethoreru_famsf_text1col9.svg"/>
        <al encoding="mdc">
        ...=k n SnA=kHr aA.wy n.w dwA.t &lt;aq&gt;=k m qar ra-nb imAx n wsir ir.t-Hr-i&lt;r&gt;w sA H&lt;r-ir&gt;=zn {f} ms &lt;n nb.t&gt; pr  
        &lt;tA&gt;-di-wsir mAa-xrw m nb mAa.t rx wsx.t n mAa.ty
        </al>
        <tr xml:lang="en">
        …your face content. You shall not be turned away from the doors of the Duat! May you (enter) the shrine every day.  Revered one of Osiris, Irethoriru, son of Herirsen, who the lady of the house  
        Tadiusir bore, justified, as a lord of truth who knows how to come out from the hall of two truths.
        </tr>
      </frag>
    </text>
  </texts>
  <footnotes>
    <fn num="1">This name should be treated as provisional, since there are no close paralels in Ranke PN
     and is spelled differently in the two places it occurs--the second being on line 9. 
    </fn>
    <fn num="2">
    WB III 106.7 for this spelling of xn.ty
    </fn>
    <fn num="3">
    According to LGG III p 810, these are underworld beings who appear in other contexts.
    </fn>
    <fn num="4">
    This may be a somewhat scrambled second person plural pronoun in which the carver slipped while making the plural strokes.
    </fn>
    <fn num="5">
    The name here is usually "Tkm." See 18th dynasty version in P. Nu and Ptolemaic version in P. Turin 1791. 
    Nekau is not otherwise known.
    </fn>
    <fn num="6">
    There is a pretty clear modern repair to the coffin lid here where a crack has been filled in, obscuring the  glyphs here.
    </fn>
    <fn num="7">
    Here, "pw" ("This") is expected, and the "ip" could be a version of the archaic "ipw"--"these."
    </fn>
    <fn num="8"> Here ends Spell 72, in the same location as the 18th Dynasty version. 
    The spell which follows is a Nut spell derived from PT 368 and common on coffins from the Saite period forward. 
    </fn>
  </footnotes>
</page>
